Winston Sharples Music Manuscripts
Music Division, Library of Congress
Guides to Special Collections in the Music Division of the Library of Congress
Winston Sharples Music Manuscripts 1943-1968
ML31.S45
Sharples, Winston, 1909-1978
2,400 items 30 containers 12 linear feet
Music Division Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Winston Sharples was an American composer best known for his work with animated short films, such as Casper, the Friendly Ghost, Popeye the Sailor, and Jeepers and Creepers. The collection consists of manuscript particells (piano scores with dialogue and cues), scores, parts, and lyric sheets related to his professional engagements.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically therein.
People
Oriolo, Joe.; Seeger, Hal.; Sharples, Winston, 1909-1978--Manuscripts.; Sharples, Winston, 1909-1978.; Sharples, Winston, 1909-1978.; Sharples, Winston, 1909-1978. Selections.
Organizations
Famous Studios (Firm)
Subjects
Animated film music--Lead sheets.; Animated film music--Scores and parts.; Animated television music--Lead sheets.; Animated television music--Scores and parts.; Motion picture music.; Music--Manuscripts.; Television music.
Administrative Information
Provenance
Gift; Winston Singleton Sharples, Jr., Mrs. Daisy Parkinson Sharples Sweet, and Michael Dante Sharples; 2005.
Accruals
No further accruals are expected.
Transfers
Sound and video recordings from the Winston Sharples Music Manuscripts have been transferred to the Library of Congress Motion Picture, Broadcasting, and Recorded Sound Division. An inventory of this material is available in the Music Division's collection file.
Access and Restrictions
The Winston Sharples Music Manuscripts are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Music Division prior to visiting in order to determine whether the desired materials will be available at that time.
Certain restrictions to use or copying of materials may apply.
Biographical Note
Winston Singleton Sharples was a composer best known for his work with animated short subjects, especially those created by the animation departments at Van Beuren Studios (1932-1936) and later at Paramount Pictures animation studios (circa 1939-1967).
Sharples was born on March 1, 1909, in Fall River, Massachusetts to William, a machinist, and Mary Sharples. He began playing piano in vaudeville at the age of eight. He earned a B.A. from Harvard University, an M.F.A. in drama from the Carnegie Institute of Technology and continued studies at the Yale University Graduate School of Drama.
Sharples appeared on radio from 1930 to 1932, playing the piano on a 15-minute morning program at various stations in Connecticut. He moved to New York City in 1932, where he played piano and occasionally bass with Vincent Lopez's orchestra.
Sharples joined Gene Rodemich in scoring cartoons for the Van Beuren Corporation (primarily an animation studio) in 1932 after Walter Winchell had praised his work with Lopez in a newspaper column, which was read by studio owner Amadee J. Van Beuren. During the next couple of years, Sharples and Rodemich composed new synchronized musical soundtracks for previously produced silent film shorts acquired by Van Bueren, including twelve Charlie Chaplin short films (1916-1918 Lone Star comedies originally produced by the Mutual Film Corporation), such as The Pawnshop and The Rink. Rodemich died in February 1934, just as the Van Beuren Studio was beginning to expand its capacity to include live action film documentaries. Sharples stayed at Van Beuren until 1936, during which time he assumed a larger musical role, composing the music for two Frank Buck documentary film vehicles, Wild Cargo (1934) and Fang and Claw (1935) and another documentary film titled Joan Lowell, Adventure Girl (1934). In the late 1930s, Sharples was associate composer for another film documentary Dark Rapture (1938), produced by Armand Denis Productions/Universal Pictures.
Sharples contributed music for the 1939 full-length animated Paramount Pictures/Max Fleischer Studio production Gulliver’s Travels. The well-known song "It’s a Hap Hap Happy Day," with music and lyrics by Sammy Timburg, Al Neiburg and Sharples, first appeared in this feature. This song, as well as many additional songs and other incidental music subsequently composed, were later compiled into a stock musical cue library that was repeatedly drawn upon for Paramount cartoons created during the next twenty-eight years.
Sharples composed music scores for the Max Fleischer Studio, the theatrical animation studio of Paramount, through 1942, first contributing music for the Superman series (1942-1943). In mid-1942, Paramount reorganized its animation studio, renaming it Famous Studios and relocating all production to New York City from the former Florida location. During the next twenty-five years, Sharples composed hundreds of music scores for Famous Studios’ various theatrical cartoon series, which included: The Cat, Comic Kings (King Features Syndicate) featuring Beetle Bailey, Barney Google and Snuffy Smith, and Krazy Kat in separate series, Fractured Fables, GoGo Toons, Harveytoons (featuring characters from Harvey Comics such as Little Audrey, Baby Huey, etc.), Herman and Katnip, Honey Halfwitch, Jeepers and Creepers, Merry Makers, Modern Madcaps, Noveltoons, Popeye the Sailor, Swifty and Shorty, and dozens of audience sing-a-long cartoons in the Screen Songs and Kartune series. In the 1960s, Sharples successfully adapted his style to smaller instrumental ensembles and even incorporated jazz and rock and roll styles for the edgier works of Ralph Bakshi, until Paramount finally closed production of theatrical cartoons in late 1967.
In addition to his animated cartoon work, Sharples composed music for several Paramount live action short films and documentaries produced during the 1940s and early 1950s. During the late 1940s, Sharples gradually assumed the position of music director for several live action short films found in Paramount's Pacemaker series, also contributing music for the Headliner, Musical Parade and Paramount News film series. Sharples composed music for at least two Paramount documentaries made in the late 1940s: The Grass is Greener (with a possible working title: Freedom’s Firepower) (date unknown), and Cassino to Korea (1950). He also composed music for another documentary film titled Men of the Forest, made for the United States Information Service. Other documentaries represented by full scores include a film simply titled Westinghouse (a possible working title), dated Jan. 17, 1952, and another documentary score that lacks any title/production details.
Sharples composed music for several episodes of the 1955 syndicated television program His Honor, Homer Bell. The program featured Gene Lockhart as Judge Homer Bell and was produced by Galahad Productions, for NBC Films.
Sharples joined ASCAP in 1948. In 1958, Sharples teamed with Joe Oriolo (best known as the creator of the Casper, the Friendly Ghost cartoon series) to produce music for 260 cartoons in the new Felix the Cat television cartoon series. That series made extensive use of stock music formerly composed for the Paramount cartoon shorts as well as newly created music such as the Felix the Cat theme song, composed by Sharples.
In the late 1950s, Sharples and animation producer Hal Seeger formed a partnership called Scroll Productions that repackaged Sharples' scores from the Paramount cartoons into a stock music library, much like the Capitol Records Hi-Q library. Most of the cues were from late 1950s productions, but some dated as far back as the 1952 Popeye cartoon Big Bad Sinbad. Other television animated productions that used this stock music included the King Features Syndicate television cartoons Popeye the Sailor, Barney Google and Snuffy Smith, Beetle Bailey, as well as King Leonardo, The Mighty Hercules, Rocket Robin Hood, Tennessee Tuxedo and the Underdog cartoon series. Later, Sharples’ music cues (along with additional cues and incidental music composed by his associate George Steiner) were recycled into episodes of Seeger's Batfink series. Sharples also composed the theme song for Seeger's Milton the Monster television cartoon show in 1965, in addition to using the stock music package for part of the underscore. During 1965-1968, Sharples contributed music to the Milton the Monster Show which featured several cartoon characters - each having its own cartoon series: Fearless Fly, Flukey Luke, Milton the Monster, Muggy Doo, Boy Cat, Muggy Doo, Boy Fox, Penny Penguin, Stuffy Durma and an unissued cartoon character series titled Wilbur the Wanted.
Winston Sharples died on April 3, 1978, at age 69, in Hilton Head, South Carolina.
Scope and Content Note
The Winston Sharples Music Manuscripts spans a period between 1943 and 1968, roughly corresponding to the years Sharples was active as principal composer for Paramount's animation production branch, Famous Studios. During this twenty-five year period, Sharples composed music for almost 700 animated short films while also serving as music director of Paramount's live action Pacemaker short films, and also contributing to other Paramount film series such as Headliner, Musical Parade, and Paramount News, and longer documentaries - some produced by other companies.
The collection contains approximently 190 Paramount cartoon scores found almost entirely in the form of holographs: particells (a form of lead sheet that contains film dialogue, descriptive action cues, other film frame specific comments and a piano score), full orchestral scores, and instrumental parts. Several photocopied manuscripts contain melodic lines with lyrics, made for Paramount's Screen Song cartoon series, while other pages contain only lyrics. Many cartoons have been identified using either a provided title, particell dialogue, or other means. Other scores are only identified by the unique Paramount job number, an in-house accession number that serves as an identifier and means of providing an approximate theatrical release date. Also included are scores, instrumental parts, musical cues (often composed by associate composer George Steiner) and other incidental music written for several mid-1960s television cartoon series produced by Joe Oriolo and Hal Seeger. These shows include The Mighty Hercules, Flukey Luke, Milton the Monster, and Penny Penguin.
Full scores for several live-action film documentaries and short films are included, such as Paramount's The Grass is Greener and Pacemaker series film Bundle from Brazil (1948). The full score of a six-reel documentary issued by the United States Information Service titled Men of the Forest is included as is a circa 1952 film titled Westinghouse that has no accompanying production details. Another film score present is Land Called New Jersey, produced by Bransby Productions. Sharples' brief foray into composing for television is represented by his music for the 1955 syndicated live action program His Honor, Homer Bell, starring Gene Lockhart and produced by Galahad Productions for NBC Films.
The remaining manuscripts in the collection consist of holograph sketches, lyric sheets, and musical fragments that have been indexed using any available descriptive information from the materials.
Organization of the Winston Sharples Music Manuscripts
The Winston Sharples Music Manuscripts are organized in four series:
Theatrical Cartoons, 1943-1967
Television Cartoons, circa 1963-1968
Live Action Films, 1940s-1950s
Miscellany, circa 1940s-1960s
http://lccn.loc.gov/2002
Container List
- Theatrical Cartoons, 1943-1967 (Box 1-14, 17-23)
  Around 190 cartoon scores from theatrical cartoons produced by Paramount's animation studio, Famous Studios. Paramount's theatrical cartoons were issued in several different series with titles such as Fractured Fables, Modern Madcaps, and Noveltoons. Original cartoon production job numbers, a unique accession identification number assigned by Famous Studios to each cartoon, are included when present and were used in dating each cartoon. The date represents the cartoon's original theatrical release date.
  Arranged alphabetically by individual cartoon series and alphabetically by title therein. Unidentified particells and full scores are arranged in numerical order by the original job number.
  - Casper, the Friendly Ghost, 1951
    - Too boo, or not to boo (N-10-11-C), 1951, Particell; Fragment (Box-folder 3/4)
  - The Cat, 1960-1961
    - Cane and able (C-20-2), 1961, Particell (Box-folder 1/1)
    - Cool cat blues (C-20-1), 1961, Particell (Box-folder 1/2)
    - Top cat (MM-20-5), 1960, Particell (Box-folder 1/3)
  - Comic Kings, 1962
    - The hat (0423), 1962, Particell (Box-folder 2/1)
    - The hat (0423), 1962, Full score (Box-folder 17/7)
    - Hero's reward (0425), 1962, Particell (Box-folder 2/2)
    - Hero's reward (0425), 1962, Full score (Box-folder 17/8)
    - Home sweet swampy (0426), 1962, Particell (Box-folder 2/3)
    - The method and maw (0422), 1962, Particell (Box-folder 2/4-6)
    - The method and maw (0422), 1962, Full score (Box-folder 17/6)
    - Snuffy's song (0421), 1962, Particell (Box-folder 3/1)
    - Snuffy's song (0421), 1962, Full score (Box-folder 17/5)
    - Take me to your gen'rul (0414), 1962, Particell (Box-folder 3/2-3)
  - Fractured Fables, 1967
    - The fuz (0619), 1967, Full score; Caption title: "Super basher" (Box-folder 18/8)
    - Mouse trek (0641), 1967, Full score (Box-folder 18/18)
    - My daddy, the astronaut (0616), 1967, Particell (Box-folder 1/4)
    - The stubborn cowboy (0628), 1967, Particell (Box-folder 1/5)
    - The stubborn cowboy (0628), 1967, Full score (Box-folder 18/15)
    - The stuck-up wolf (0634), 1967, Particell (Box-folder 1/6)
    - The stuck-up wolf (0634), 1967, Full score (Box-folder 18/7)
  - GoGo Toons, 1967
    - A bridge grows in Brooklyn (0618), 1967, Particell (Box-folder 1/7)
    - A bridge grows in Brooklyn (0618), 1967, Full score (Box-folder 18/7)
    - Keep the cool, baby (0627), 1967, Particell (Box-folder 1/8)
    - Keep the cool, baby (0627), 1967, Full score (Box-folder 18/14)
    - The plumber (0614), 1967, Particell (Box-folder 1/9)
    - The plumber (0614), 1967, Full score (Box-folder 18/5)
    - The space squid (0613), 1967, Particell (Box-folder 1/10)
    - The space squid (0613), 1967, Full score (Box-folder 18/4)
    - The squaw-path (0615), 1967, Particell (Box-folder 1/11)
    - The squaw-path (0615), 1967, Full score (Box-folder 18/6)
  - Herman and Katnip, 1953, 1959
    - Felineous assault (HK-18-4), 1959, Particell (Box-folder 5/1)
    - Fun on furlough (HK-18-5), 1959, Particell (Box-folder 5/2)
    - Of mice and magic (N-11-9), 1953, Particell (Box-folder 5/3)
    - Owly to bed (HK-18-3), 1959, Particell (Box-folder 5/4)
  - Honey Halfwitch, 1967
    - Alter egotist (0623), 1967, Particell (Box-folder 10/6)
    - Alter egotist (0623), 1967, Full score (Box-folder 18/11)
    - Brother bat (0626), 1967, Particell (Box-folder 10/7)
    - Clean sweep (0624), 1967, Particell (Box-folder 10/8)
    - Clean sweep (0624), 1967, Full score (Box-folder 18/12)
    - High but not dry (0625), 1967, Particell (Box-folder 10/9)
    - High but not dry (0625), 1967, Full score (Box-folder 18/13)
  - Jeepers and Creepers, 1960
    - The boss is always right (N-19-3), 1960, Particell (Box-folder 5/5)
    - Busy buddies (N-19-15), 1960, Particell (Box-folder 5/6)
    - Scouting for trouble (N-19-17), 1960, Particell (Box-folder 5/7)
  - Kartune, 1953
    - Hysterical history (SS-12-3), 1953, Particell (Box-folder 3/5)
    - Vegetable vaudeville (unknown number), 1951, Parts; Featured song: "Yes! We have no bananas" (Box-folder 23/2)
  - Little Lulu, circa 1943-1944
    - Lulu's birthday party (unknown number), 1944, Part with lyrics; Featured song: "Birthday party" (Box-folder 23/3)
    - Little Lulu series theme song, circa 1943, Vocal part (Box-folder 23/4)
  - Merry Makers, 1967
    - Forget-me-nuts (0633), 1967, Particell (Box-folder 3/6)
    - Forget-me-nuts (0633), 1967, Full score (Box-folder 18/16)
    - From orbit to obit (MM-20-6), 1967, Particell (Box-folder 3/7)
    - From orbit to obit (MM-20-6), 1967, Full score (Box-folder 3/8)
  - Modern Madcaps, 1959-1967
    - And so Tibet (0556), 1964, Particell (Box-folder 7/1)
    - A balmy knight (0583), 1966, Particell (Box-folder 7/2)
    - The blacksheep blacksmith (0621), 1967, Particell (Box-folder 7/3)
    - The blacksheep blacksmith (0621), 1967, Full score (Box-folder 18/9)
    - Bopin' Hood (C-20-3), 1961, Particell (Box-folder 7/4)
    - Bouncing Benny (MM-20-1), 1960, Particell (Box-folder 7/5)
    - Crumley Cogwheel (0512), 1962, Particell (Box-folder 7/6)
    - Disguise the limit (MM-19-2), 1960, Particell (Box-folder 7/7)
    - Electronica (N-19-8), 1960, Particell (Box-folder 7/8)
    - Fiddle-faddle (N-19-2), 1960, Particell (Box-folder 7/9)
    - Fit to be toyed (N-18-6), 1959, Particell (Box-folder 7/10)
    - From dime to dime (N-19-7), 1960, Particell (Box-folder 8/1)
    - Galaxia (MM-20-2), 1960, Particell (Box-folder 8/2)
    - Giddy gadgets (0514), 1962, Particell (Box-folder 8/3)
    - I want my mummy (0584), 1966, Full score (Box-folder 18/3)
    - In the nicotine (MM-20-8), 1961, Particell (Box-folder 8/4)
    - The inquisit visit (MM-20-9), 1961, Particell (Box-folder 8/5)
    - The itch (0566), 1965, Particell (Box-folder 8/6)
    - The itch (0566), 1965, Full score (Box-folder 18/1)
    - The mighty termite (MM-20-7), 1961, Particell (Box-folder 8/7)
    - Mike the masquerader (N-18-10), 1959, Particell (Box-folder 8/8)
    - Near sighted and far out (0563), 1964, Particell (Box-folder 8/9)
    - One of the family (0521), 1962, Particell (Box-folder 8/10)
    - One of the family (0521), 1962, Full score (Box-folder 17/9)
    - One weak vacation (0525), 1963, Particell (Box-folder 9/1)
    - One weak vacation (0525), 1963, Full score (Box-folder 17/10)
    - The outside dope (0565), 1965, Particell (Box-folder 9/2)
    - The outside dope (0565), 1965, Full scores (2) (Box-folder 17/13)
    - Penny pals (0315), 1962, Particell (Box-folder 9/3)
    - Penny pals (0315), 1962, Full score (Box-folder 17/2)
    - Le petite parade (N-18-7), 1959, Particell (Box-folder 9/4)
    - The phantom moustacher (MM-20-4), 1961, Particell (Box-folder 9/5)
    - The plot sickens (0511), 1961, Particell (Box-folder 9/6)
    - Poor little witch girl (0567), 1965, Particell (Box-folder 9/7)
    - Poor little witch girl (0567), 1965, Full score; First cartoon appearance of Honey Halfwitch (Box-folder 18/2)
    - Reading, writhing and 'rithmetic (0557), 1964, Particell (Box-folder 9/8)
    - The shoe must go on (MM-19-1), 1960, Particell (Box-folder 9/9)
    - Shootin' stars (N-19-10), 1960, Particell (Box-folder 10/1)
    - Terry the terror (MM-20-3), 1960, Particell (Box-folder 10/2)
    - Trigger treats (N-19-4), 1960, Particell (Box-folder 10/3)
    - Trouble date (N-19-5), 1960, Particell (Box-folder 10/4)
    - A wedding knight (0585), 1966, Particell (Box-folder 10/5)
  - Noveltoons, 1952-1967
    - L'amour the merrier (N-17-9), 1957, Particell (Box-folder 11/1)
    - Be mice to cats (N-19-11), 1960, Particell (Box-folder 11/2)
    - Butterscotch and soda (unknown number), 1948, Part with lyrics; Featured song: "The tummy-ache blues", lyrics by Buddy Kaye (Box-folder 23/6)
    - Cape Kidnaveral (N-20-6), 1961, Particell (Box-folder 11/3)
    - Case of the cockeyed carnary (N-12-7), 1952, Particell (Box-folder 11/4)
    - Cock-o-doodle dino (N-16-4), 1957, Particell (Box-folder 11/5)
    - Counter attack (N-19-16), 1960, Particell (Box-folder 11/6)
    - Dante dreamer (N-17-4), 1958, Particell (Box-folder 11/7)
    - Feast and furious (N-11-11), 1952, Particell (Box-folder 11/8)
    - Fiddlin' around (0324), 1962, Particell (Box-folder 11/9)
    - Fiddlin' around (0324), 1962, Full score (Box-folder 17/3)
    - Fine feathered friend (N-19-14), 1960, Particell (Box-folder 12/1)
    - Good snooze tonight (0325), 1963, Particell (Box-folder 12/2)
    - Good snooze tonight (0325), 1963, Full score (Box-folder 17/4)
    - A hair-raising tale (0560), 1965, Particell (Box-folder 12/3)
    - A hair-raising tale (0560), 1965, Full score (Box-folder 17/12)
    - Hobo's holiday (unknown number), 1963, Instrumental parts with lyrics; Featured song: "Big rock candy mountain" (Box-folder 23/7)
    - Homer on the range (0559), 1964, Particell (Box-folder 12/4)
    - Horning in (0562), 1965, Particell (Box-folder 12/5)
    - Hound about that (N-20-5), 1961, Particell (Box-folder 12/6)
    - Houndabout (N-18-8), 1959, Particell (Box-folder 12/7)
    - Huey's Father's Day (N-18-9), 1959, Particell (Box-folder 12/8)
    - Kozmo goes to school (0311), 1961, Particell (Box-folder 12/9)
    - Kozmo goes to school (0311), 1961, Full score (Box-folder 17/1)
    - The lion's busy (N-20-4), 1961, Particell (Box-folder 12/10)
    - Little Audrey says - theme song (unknown number), circa 1948, Vocal part; Introductory them song for Little Audrey cartoons (Box-folder 23/5)
    - Miceniks (N-20-2), 1960, Particell (Box-folder 13/1)
    - Monkey doodles (N-19-9), 1960, Particell (Box-folder 13/2)
    - Mr. Money Gags (N-16-6), 1957, Particell (Box-folder 13/3)
    - Northern mites (N-20-3), 1960, Particell (Box-folder 13/4)
    - Okey dokey donkey (N-17-5), 1958, Particell (Box-folder 13/5)
    - Op, pop, wham, and bop (0575), 1966, Particell (Box-folder 13/6)
    - Out of this whirl (N-19-1), 1959, Particell (Box-folder 13/7)
    - Peck your own home (N-19-12), 1960, Particell (Box-folder 13/8)
    - Planet Mouseola (N-20-1), 1960, Particell (Box-folder 13/9)
    - Robin hoodwinked (0622), 1967, Particell (Box-folder 14/1)
    - Robin hoodwinked (0622), 1967, Full score (Box-folder 18/10)
    - The sheepish wolf (0334), 1963, Particell (Box-folder 14/2)
    - Sick transit (0576), 1966, Particell (Box-folder 14/3)
    - Silly science (MM-19-3), 1960, Particell (Box-folder 14/4)
    - Sir Irving and Jeames (N-16-5), 1956, Particell; Fragment (Box-folder 14/5)
    - Song of the birds (unknown number), 1949, Instrumental parts; Featured instrumental selection: "Bird funeral" (Box-folder 23/8)
    - Starting from hatch (N-12-1), 1953, Particell (Box-folder 14/6)
    - The story of George Washington (0561), 1965, Particell (Box-folder 14/7)
    - Tarts and flowers (unknown number), 1950, Lyrics only; Featured song: "The wedding of the gingerbread man", lyrics by Buddy Kaye (Box-folder 23/9)
    - Teacher's pest (unknown number), 1950, Instrumental parts; Featured song: "The song of Wisey the Owl" (Box-folder 23/10)
    - A tiger's tail (0544), 1964, Particell (Box-folder 14/8)
    - Trick or tree (N-20-7x), 1961, Particell (Box-folder 14/9)
    - Turning the fables (N-19-13), 1960, Particell (Box-folder 14/10)
    - Turtle scoop (N-20-8), 1961, Particell (Box-folder 14/11)
  - Popeye the Sailor, 1950, 1952-1953, 1957
    - Ancient fistory (P-12-6), 1953, Particell (Box-folder 4/1)
    - Big bad Sinbad (P-12-5), 1952, Particell (Box-folder 4/2)
    - Child sockology (P-12-4), 1953, Particell (Box-folder 4/3)
    - Farmer and the belle (P-10-6), 1950, Particell (Box-folder 4/4)
    - Patriotic Popeye (P-16-2), 1957, Particell (Box-folder 4/5)
    - Swimmer take all (P-11-7), 1952, Particell (Box-folder 4/6)
    - Popeye song, undated, Full score; Unidentified song (Box-folder 4/7)
  - Screen Songs, 1948-1951
    - The big drip (unknown number), 1949, Parts and lyric sheets; Featured song: "It ain't gonna rain no more" (Box-folder 22/1)
    - The big flame up (SS-8-12), 1949, Parts; Featured song: "There'll be a hot time in the old town tonight" (Box-folder 22/2)